Guide to the Attila Kotányi Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Attila Kotányi papers
1940-2000
GEN MSS 1499
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
10.33
(9 boxes)
Kotányi, Attila
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Jan Ceuleers on the Frederick W. Hilles Fund, 2012.
Arrangement
Materials collection roughly maintain the order found at time of acquisition.
Attila Kotányi
Attila Kotányi (1924-2003) was a Hungarian poet, philosopher, and architect associated with the Situationist International.
Content Description
The collection consists of correspondence, notes, index cards, notebooks, photographs, artwork, architectural drawings, blueprints, research materials, printed material, and other papers by or relating to Attila Kotanyi and documenting his life, work, and involvement with the Situationist International.
Counterculture -- Europe; Architectural drawings; Drawings; Photographs; Situationism -- France; Kotányi, Attila; Internationale situationniste
- Correspondence, circa 1946-2000s (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains letters to and from Attila Kotányi.
  Also contains: a letter to Guy Debord (1963 October 11); a letter from Laszlo Moholy-Nagy, Institute of Design in Chicago (1946 November 11); a postcard to Szabo (1957 August 21); a note from Hannes Böhringer (1983); a letter from Roberto Ohrt (1984 September 28); a letter from Raoul Vaneigem (circa 2000); letters in Hungarian from different correspondents (circa 1950s-1980s).
- Notes, 1947-1990; 3.67; (4 boxes)
  - Megbeszélés müszaki-pedgogiai, 1947 (Box 1)
    A debate on technical-pedagogical matters. Contains: a transcript of the debate, which concerned the teaching of architecture. Attila Kotányi was one of the participants.
  - Notes, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1958 (Box 1)
    Contains notes, written in English, about the uses of psychology, psychotherapy and its links to architecture. Also contains notes on the Brussels World Fair of 1958, and the role of UNESCO.
  - Notes, 1959 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on psychology, alternatives for religion, and "la grande révision". Also contains notes on the "irrational" elements in Marxism.
  - Notes, 1960 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on Asger Jorn's interpretations on dialectics, the uses of a situationist critque, the meaning of de Sade for the urban planner, Friedrich Nietzsche's warnings concerning "socialism", the dangers of subtlety and of unnecessary complicated reasoning, and "la beauté c'est la promesse d'une fonction." Also contains notes on the danger and necessity of irrational factors.
  - Notes, 1961 (Box 1)
    Contains notes taken during the fifth conference of the Situationist International, held in Göteborg, Sweden (1961 August 28-30).
  - Notes, 1962 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on the themes discussed within the Situationist International. Also contains notes on the abolishing of reigning information systems in order to liberate general consciousness from the "raison d'état", real spontaneousness as opposed to the fake version that comes with the official addiction (i.e. television), the rhythm of meetings and separations within the Situationist International, and the role of time in art.
  - Notes, 1963 (Box 1)
    Contains a typescript entitled "Introduction et Apostyle à la critique cacoteuse." Also contains a draft of an announcement of "grand spectacle antisituationniste," as well as notes regarding "contre l'idéologie du hasard," and "pour la révalorisation commerciale de l'art, antisituationniste, ou l'art tout simplement."
  - Notes, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1966 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on architecture, urban planning, philosophical subjects, Martin Heidegger's ideas on dwellings, and architecture as "oeuvre totale".
  - Notes, 1967 (Box 1)
    Contains a notebook, titled "Ingolstadt," as well as handwritten notes.
  - Notes, 1968 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on philosophy, gangsters, an illustrated fable of the wahlfish, and other related subjects.
  - Notes, 1969 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on Dada, and other related subjects.
  - Notes, 1970 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on architecture, with drawings and self portraits, as well as other related subjects.
  - Notes, 1971 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on Joseph Beuys and the Akademie of Düsseldor, along with self-portrait drawings, and other related subjects.
  - Notes, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1973 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on Michel Foucault, as well as Max Taut in Japan.
  - Notes, 1974 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on the contradictions of rational planning, as well as freedom and cybernetics. Also contains notes on the contradictions between scientific and religious attitudes regarding reality.
  - Notes, 1975 (Box 1)
    Contains notes regarding Guy Debord, the Baader-Meinhof Group, violence, and urban planning.
  - Notes, 1976 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on "form and function," technological and economical contexts, the search for meaning, art, and other related subjects.
  - Notes, 1977 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on social complexity, Paul Rudolph and mega structures, postmodernism, Venturi and Raunch, and other related subjects.
  - Notes, 1978 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on religion as an antidote for reductionism, and other related subjects.
  - Notes, 1979 (Box 1)
    Contains notes on Christopher Lasch, Jean Baudrillard, Zen discipline, and other related subjects.
  - Notes, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1981-1990 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Index cards, circa 1982-1989 (Box 2)
    Contains index cards with handwritten notes.
  - Index cards, circa 1981-1990 (Box 3)
  - Index cards, circa 1985 (Box 4)
- Notebooks, 1955-1979-06-17; 2.17; (2 boxes)
  - Notebook, 1955-1956 (Box 5)
    Contains drawings.
  - Notebook, 1957-08-18 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1958-1959 (Box 5)
    Contains drawings and clippings.
  - Notebook, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, 1964; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Contains two notebooks, with drawings.
  - Notebook, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, 1965; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1966-01-1966-04 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1966-05-25 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1966-06 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1966-06-20 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1966-08 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1966-08-13 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1966-09-16 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, circa 1967 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1967-01-18 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1967-01-20 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1967-02 (Box 5)
    Contains drawings. Also contains a newspaper clipping.
  - Notebook, 1967-05-09 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1967-05-28 (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, circa 1968; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-01-17 (Box 5)
    Contains drawings and newspaper clippings.
  - Notebook, 1968-03 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-03-12 (Box 5)
    Contains a newspaper clipping.
  - Notebook, 1968-03-22 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-03-28-1968-04-01 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-04-01 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-04-04 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-04-07 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-04-09 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-04-18 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-05-03 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-05-18 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-06-17 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-06-29 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1968-07-10 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-07-23 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-07-25 (Box 6)
    Contains clipping and drawings.
  - Notebook, 1968-08 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-08-14 (Box 6)
  - Notebooks, 1968-09; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-09-07 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-09-13 (Box 6)
    Contains clippings and drawings.
  - Notebook, 1968-10-07 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-10-20 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-11-01-1968-11-10 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-11-22 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-11-28 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-12-06 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-12-16 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1968-12-31 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, circa 1969 (Box 6)
    Contains clippings.
  - Notebook, 1969-02-01 (Box 6)
    Includes drawings.
  - Notebook, 1969-02-26 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1969-03-24 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1969-04-28 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1969-06-25 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1969-07-15 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1969-07-17 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1969-08-07 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1969-10-03 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1973-01-31 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1975-06-16 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1975-08-03 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1975-12-01 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, circa 1976 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1976-03-25 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1976-05-05 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1976-05-18-1976-05-25 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1976-12 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1976-06-03 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1978-02-23 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, 1979-04-04-1979-06-17 (Box 6)
- Photographs, undated (Box 7)
  Contains photographs of architectural models, as well as a photograph of a drip painting, and a photographic negative.
- Drawings, 1956-1980; 3.42; (2 boxes)
  - Architectural drawings, circa 1956-1962; 2 folders (Box 7)
    Contains sketches for architectural and urban projects.
  - Artistic drawings, circa 1956-1980s (Box 7)
    Contains stylized portraits and self portraits, as well as landscapes and abstracts.
  - Artistic drawings, circa 1956-1980s; 3 folders (Box 8 (Oversize))
    Contains large format impressionist and abstract artwork.
  - Blueprints, circa 1957-1965; 2 folders (Box 7)
    Contains drawings and blueprints for an urban project, created when Attila Kotányi worked at the Herbosch architectural office within Brussels (circa 1957). Also contains blueprints of a project designed by Attila Kotányi of artists' studios and apartments (circa 1965).
- Bibliographie, circa 1957 (Box 7)
  Contains bibliographical notes.
- Sanierung des Lebens, Sanierung der Stadt, 1979-05-22 (Box 7)
  Contains notes, in German, on city planning.
- Szabo Lajos Kepiro Dialektikaja, circa 1988-1992 (Box 7)
  Contains photocopied document with handwritten corrections and additions.
- Biographical information, 1962-1982 (Box 7)
  Also contains documents related to Attila Kotányi's teaching at the Düsseldorf Academy.
- Scientia sacra, circa 1940s (Box 7)
  Contains bound typescripts regarding the spirtual tradition of mankind, especially regarding cults and culture, and the anthropology of antiquity.
- Paul Wiener. Une manifestation du malaise dans la civilisation: le salopart, undated (Box 7)
  Contains a critique of pop art and nouveau réalisme.
- Eckehardt, undated (Box 7)
  Contains material regarding Friedrich Nietzsche and Meister Eckhardt.
- Works by other authors, undated (Box 7)
  Contains material regarding Győző Határ, Magyar Balázs, Günter Rösch, and Gerhard Fehl.
- Printed material, 1950-1999; 2.17; (2 boxes)
  Contains books with extensive marginalia, as well as exhibit catalogs and school material.
  - Printed material, circa 1954-1999 (Box 7)
    Contains a 1982 program from the Akademie der Architektenkammer Nordrhein-Westfalen, a photocopy of "Grundgedanken des Buddhismus," by Martin Brauen (1983 February), a photocopy of "Im Zeichen des Buddhismus" (1982), a photocopy of "Wir sind die Autoren unserer eigenen Geschichte," by Monica Moebius, a newspaper clipping, a photocopy of "Proof In Philosopy," by Professor Charles Perelman (Hibbert Journal, 1954), Endre Bíró translation work regarding James Joyce, a photostat of "Renate Marschner: Die Frankfurter Schule," a photostat of "Bodenproben," by Hannes Böhringer (1987), and a photocopy of "Noten Zum Surrealismus," by Jacob Taubes (1966).
  - Staatliche Kunstakademie Düsseldorf, printed material, 1976-1989; 3 folders (Box 9)
    Contains school catalogs, with handwritten marginalia and placed-in notes.
  - Zeitung 2, Staatliche Kunstakademie Düsseldorf, newspaper, 1982-12 (Box 9)
  - Anschlag, Nos. 1 and 2, periodicals, 1964-08-1964-11 (Box 9)
    Both periodicals have extensive marginalia, by Attila Kotányi.
  - Der Französische Strukturalismus, by Günther Schiwy, book, 1969 (Box 9)
    Contains extensive marginalia, with a laid-in note.
  - A l'ombre des majorités silencieuses ou la fin du social, by Jean Baudrillard, book, 1978 (Box 9)
    Contains extensive marginalia.
  - Paul Ricoeur ou la liberté selon l'espérance, by Michel Philibert, book, 1971 (Box 9)
    Contains extensive marginalia, with a placed-in note.
  - Warum schaffen sie es nicht wie wir Klangkörper den glücksbringenden Pfad zu erwischen, by Attila Kotányi, book., 1999 (Box 9)
  - Retrospective de Lajos Vajda (1908-1941), exhibit catalog, 1978-07-1978-09 (Box 9)
  - Kommunikációm: Kovács Tibor, exhibit catalog, 1999 (Box 9)
  - Origine et fonction de la culture, by Géza Róheim, book, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Die Seele im technischen Zeitalter, by Arnold Gehlen, book, 1957 (Box 9)
    Contains extensive marginalia, with laid-in notes.
  - L'Effet Beaubourg, by Jean Baudrillard, book, 1977 (Box 9)
  - La Dialectique de la durée, by Gaston Bachelard, book, 1950 (Box 9)
  - La dialectique, by Paul Foulquié, book, 1953 (Box 9)
    Contains extensive marginalia, with placed-in notes.
  - Burano Kommunikation Sozio-Ökonomie Städtebau..., by Christof von Dellemann, book, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Kunstakademie Düsseldorf. Studienarbeiten aus den Architekturklassen, exhibition catalog, 1979 (Box 9)
  - Ästhetik der Landschaft: Gesamthochschule Kassel, catalog, 1977 (Box 9)
    Contains marginalia.